in terms of the
the attitude that one should have when
beginning
to look into the suitors to start the
path to try to understand what the buddha is
to try to understand what the buddha is
saying
is that one must understand that you you
don't know
yeah that is pretty much prerequisite
but that seems to be overlooked
pretty much because most people start
off with i know
quite a bit already well no they start
with i don't know
but as soon as they get to know
something that becomes or now i know
everybody starts i don't know but the
first port of call i become familiar with oh i
port of call i become familiar with oh i
tried this suit
or i heard from that teacher okay and
now they already gave me a basis which
is inevitable it has to happen
you become more familiar but the
slightest sort of familiarity then gets conceived
sort of familiarity then gets conceived
as knowledge
misconceived as knowledge so now i'm
familiar with it
and you immediately start assuming that
that's now you know what dhamma is
so like again to give an example say you
don't know anything
you heard about buddhism seems
interesting you want to learn to
meditate want to feel yourself from suffering
want to feel yourself from suffering
maybe in whatever vague terms
you relate to that thought and then you
go i don't know and listen to talk
from some terrible other monk and then
you start reading the sutes
and now you know more more familiar
you've got more information
information is not the knowledge like
have you understood it like well yes i
understood it to some degree because
i make sense out of it i can explain to
somebody else
that's fine but that is mundane that's
not the understanding that's not even
the beginning of understanding
so if you don't forsake the mundane idea
of understanding
you will not then develop this
supramundane which is
the understanding the understanding that
frees you from suffering
because that is the beginning of
understanding knowing the four noble
truths as those very same suitors describe so
as those very same suitors describe so
here you are
thinking your understanding because
you're familiar with it you read it so
many times you have all the information
all the etymology
but you're overlooking the fact that
yeah but do i know the way out of
suffering all of this is great but have if i were
all of this is great but have if i were
to understand
one suit the left alone many i would be
at least the soda panda
if i were to understand in the way that
matters and that's the understanding
because if you use the same word for
understanding as in if you
well that's understanding but also my um
familiarity with of information is also
understanding well then you will not push yourself
well then you will not push yourself
into that understanding they will free
you from suffering
because you somehow believe that
understanding of reformation pertains to
understanding from an
uh way out of suffering and it doesn't
there is no linear uh guaranteed
sort of step by step you read this suta
then read this suta then read that suta
and then use urban
now how do you become celebrated well by
understanding what sort of panel is
so yes you need some information to
start as in to know where to
think in what direction to go but
unless you make that effort regardless
of the information
and certainly not impeded by thinking
you unders
understanding of information is the
understanding of the freedom from
suffering
then you will make that effort
and and that's all you need to do it's
not about not reading the suttas because
i end up thinking i understood
well that's another problem now so how
how do we know what to understand
if you're not reading the instruction
yeah exactly
so what you want to do is keep reading
the suttas keep listening to the talks
but keep reflecting upon it to the point
of if you were to understand it
understand it you will be free from
suffering if you're not being free from
suffering as in
free from liability to suffer not just
oh yes it helped me deal with something
no no
it helped me not experience suffering
amidst the same
circumstances that used to cause me to
suffer that should be the norm that's
the bare minimum by the way
and the only reason people don't seek
that as a bare minimum is because they
deny that that's a bare minimum
they lower the bar even more and say no
familiarity of understanding familiarity
of information
and i get my head around it that's
already the minimum well it's not
the minimum is being free from suffering
the minimum is not being
still subjected to possibility of you
know peril if you're reborn in a lower
realm so the minimum is the right view
and again one who's one who has derived
the one who sees the dhamma
which means with other view you are not
seeing the dhamma so how can you be
saying your familiarity of information
that talks about dharma is understanding
of the dharma to some extent
no can you you don't know what is right
and wrong exactly what you don't know
is right which is wrong
and that's that's the problem
so you want to keep the industries you
want to keep listening to talks but you
also want to be reflective
so if you're not being free from
suffering it's due to it's only possible
because of the two
there can only be two reasons for it
either the instruction that you're listening is
the instruction that you're listening is
wrong
or you're not properly attending to it
you you haven't
but fundamentally so you you kind of
question okay so is this instruction
correct well i can't quite tell but i can use my
well i can't quite tell but i can use my
intelligence to narrow it down
which is least likely to be wrong the
instruction so that's always like lean towards the
so that's always like lean towards the
suttas talks either about the suitors
they will push you into reading suitors
because that is again you don't know for
sure the suit is the right either
but you have to start somewhere and that
is least likely to be wrong
and that's the best you can do but again
not okay so now the suit is at least likely
okay so now the suit is at least likely
to be wrong
i believe in the suttas done deal well
no but now you have to start working
yes you're very familiar yes you
understand you're making lots of sense
with them
but are you being freed from liability
to suffer
are you praying even before the
suffering right is that understanding
resulting in you being
unable to experience dukkha
not like hiding from the dukkha or
avoiding things just no
i'm simply unable even amidst things
that used to cause me to suffer
mind cannot experience it like the
the water just just falls off those
those leaves
in the jungle it's just they don't get
wet it's just fully just doesn't matter
how much water you throw at it
just runs down cannot soak you
so in this suta majjimnikaya 70
buddha says i do not say that final
knowledge actual knowledge is achieved all at once
actual knowledge is achieved all at once
on the contrary final knowledge is
achieved by gradual training by gradual
practice by gradual progress and how is this
by gradual progress and how is this
done one who has faith in a teacher
so what is the gradual training yeah one
who has
faith in a teacher visits him yeah and
that's already what i said
so faith in the teacher corresponds to
okay who's least likely to be wrong based on
who's least likely to be wrong based on
my discerning
capabilities like i don't know way out
of suffering
but i have my intelligence intact i can
think for myself
so which is least likely to be wrong
so then you seek out when you find out
what is least likely to be wrong
what seems to be pertaining to that
which might free you from suffering you put
might free you from suffering you put
faith in it not
for its own sake not as its own goal but
just faith in terms of okay i'll apply this
faith in terms of okay i'll apply this
literally like choosing a medicine
now you can all this this is least this
is most promising medicine
but you will never know unless you start
applying it and following the
instructions a particular diet a particular lifestyle
a particular diet a particular lifestyle
avoiding certain things so the medicine
can start to work
but even then you need to wait you need
to keep doing it gradually until then
so that's what i mean it's not like the
measure of medicine working is then the
measure of ah
i am healing from suffering healing from
the possibility
to suffer so that's the true freedom
when you know that you can't suffer even
amidst things that would
make everybody else suffer now because
you learn to focus on your nostrils or
you learn to do this
they're quick to respond no simply
you're abandoned craving
through understanding so you're unable
to suffer regardless of the
circumstances to the point that it would have said if
to the point that it would have said if
you're in ireland you would have
you could have robbers chopping up your
limbs one by one like utter savages
and you would not experience duke on
that account
you will not hate them you will not have
any aversion in your mind towards them
so the gradual teaching begins with that
faith that is a prerequisite for the
that is a prerequisite for the
application of effort
not faith that's a prerequisite for this
superstitious belief that now i chant
the suttas
and i read the sutas and i bow to the
suitors and i have the unwavering faith
that the buddha was right although i
don't know for myself
no that's not the faith we're talking
about it's the faith you have in a
doctor you know there's some proper quacks then
you know there's some proper quacks then
there's some somebody who's
seems more knowledgeable than somebody
who seems more known and wise as well
so you choose wisely yourself which one
but you have to apply some medicine you
have to start somewhere
and then maybe say okay this doctor
helped me to some extent but
have i applied the medication correctly
have i really understood
the the the instructions or have i just
glanced over it
and impatiently
yeah so always twofold yes the
instruction but not just
oh he might be saying wrong things but
have i actually really understood this
to full extent
and that's even what the buddha himself
did before he became the buddha
when he was with different teachers he
would then go and
present back to them what he understood
and they would yes that's exactly what
i'm teaching
you are equal to me come set we lead
this community together
your understanding is exactly where
we're right and it says okay
thank you but that's not enough for me
so like have you understood that
so that's what i mean even if you choose
oh this is wrong you want to know why
it's wrong
like say you start following some doctor
some dumber talk whatever but then you're not
dumber talk whatever but then you're not
being free from suffering and then you
decide it's wrong because now you find
something better
be it as it may do you know
how why to what extent was this
wrong because if it if if you understood
it you would know that it's wrong
or are you just dismissing it as wrong
because it stopped inspiring you just
because you got lazy or whatever
so that's what i mean whether it's right
or wrong needs to be understood as right
or as wrong
and it can be understood if you keep
applying that effort to understand the
point so what is the instruction here what is
so what is the instruction here what is
the goal here
what is the teaching here what are the
implications here
but none of that you can develop or even
invest effort if you haven't had
faith to begin with if you're just
looking for faults in all the doctors
yeah they seems pretty good but me i'm
not sure
yeah i'm not sure i'm not sure you're
not applying anything
because if you're truly in a position to
choose right and wrong you wouldn't need
doctors to be helping you so that's why
first and foremost is wait i need help
i am not free from suffering
let me not think that i know when i
don't because if i do know
i would be free from suffering and i
wouldn't need any instruction
and yeah time might be short so don't
spend too much time picking and choosing
but instead discern apply
reflect and then yeah a person could go
you know pretty much anywhere really you
know some monastery
you know yes but they have to figure out
is it right or is it wrong but even if
you've understand that it's wrong
that would be to your benefit yeah that
would be your rightness
oh yeah this is this is why it's wrong
yeah it would benefit you actually no
that's what i mean like even when i say
to people
when sometimes they ask for a monastery
to go is like really
all you need is a monastery where where
like say
they will not be forcing views in books
on you
as in if you read anything that deviates
from this
you'll be expelled because there are
places like that you know if there are
he's into sutas or he's into whatever
this teacher or that teacher as long as
i suppose buddhist
uh that's fine if they let you study on
your own
do your own study that's fine and if the
the place keeps the vinai
you don't need more even if everything
else is oh yeah they have these views
and senior monks have such views and
wrong views none of that is your problem
that's like now you
worrying about a state of the medical
profession in general
no you only need a doctor that knows
that you can apply
if you can't find the one that knows
directly well find the instruction from
those who knew
and keep a need environment to keep
applying it environment where you can
keep the vineyard
have enough solitude and keep studying
to the point of
developing understanding doesn't mean
study i don't mean just study
and collect information but make effort
to reflect
so from that point of view many of the
monasteries would meet the criteria yeah
you will have pointless tasks and duties
but none of that is really
a fundamental issue unless of course you
spend 20 hours of your day doing meaningless
20 hours of your day doing meaningless
things
yeah yeah i'll just continue with that
gradual so the faith he visits
visits that person that he has faith in
if he can if not he googles it
he pays respects to him he gives
ear so you're ready gives air means what
i said
you don't look for fault it's full stop
so you need to learn how not to look how
not to confuse like looking for faults
tends to be confused for uh
discriminating so if i tell you don't
look for fault
okay so i must stop discriminating no
you still look
right is right wrong is wrong try to
discern see for yourself
you just don't look for faults so don't
make your discrimination personal
and you won't be looking for faults
because that's really what fault finding
is your sole problem is to understand
what's being said
and if it's wrong to understand why it's
wrong and if it feels right to
understand why it's right
if you don't make it personal you will
not look for faults
so even if you're saying something wrong
i will not be
ah he's wrong he's wrong no it's just
what's being said
doesn't fit and i understand to this
extent that it doesn't fit
now you might tell me back that i
misunderstood you and then you'd
explain in and out but maybe you will
then learn something
but if i just look for faults means i
haven't understood
why you are wrong the wrongness of that
because i put myself first
see by looking for faults in you i imply
i'm better
it's implicit it's automatic because
even what you're expressing if it's
wrong it's not a personal thing for you either
it's not a personal thing for you either
or if it is for you
doesn't need to be my personal thing
like you might be taking it personally
but it's not my problem
so don't look for fault means be open to
hear what's being said
without the kind of sort of a bit of a
reserve like um you have no criteria what fits
like um you have no criteria what fits
and what's true so you need to really
commit to the instruction and understand it
to the instruction and understand it
fully through and through and then if it
were wrong it would become evident
without needing to make it personal
because oh the instruction was wrong
because there is such and such
discrepancy and i understood it and i understood the
and i understood it and i understood the
extent of it
and i can explain it because i
understood it that's what i used to do
like um go to the library in the
monastery like books of any kind not any kind but
like books of any kind not any kind but
mean like
buddhism but from all sorts of
very broad spectrum of teachers and
traditions so there are certain things that you
so there are certain things that you
kind of know obviously are wrong
but i would take those books because
it's not enough just oh this is wrong
because it's a different tradition
i need to understand as i start reading
it why this is wrong
i need to explain to myself and to
others if somebody to ask me
now see nagarjuna view was wrong for
such and such reason
not like oh he's wrong if he's wrong
means he might
he must be contradicting at some point
some aspect of the teaching so i'm not
like fishing for
no if you understand it fully because he
might be right
and that's why it's frightening
especially in the beginning fills you
with anxiety because oh this is wrong
but then you start thinking but what if
i don't see it as wrong
yeah that's the real risk means then
what you think you understood you
haven't so if you don't run away from that
so if you don't run away from that
anxiety
and accept it and then read through it
then you'll actually
that is the work i'm undoing my own
mistaken notions to understanding wrong
view as wrong
view i'm developing my own
correct notions by understanding right
view as right view
but if i were looking for faults
ah that's it or just read the moment it
displeases me
it's wrong yeah i would never understand
wrong is wrong which means i will never
understand writers right
and your criteria for right and wrong is
just how you feel
fully emotional yeah as always you
haven't changed yeah exactly
you might have refined it but
fundamentally it's still simply based on
how you feel
and that's that's not a great idea like
terrifying that's not a criteria yeah
and why'd you like that about that well
i don't know because the first retreat i
went was theravada and i liked the
feeling and that's it yeah completely
and that's it yeah completely
circumstantial and by the way for the
same reason people like the
non-theravada yeah completely they went into that
yeah completely they went into that
direction and like oh no this is this is
my path
well what is the path path is that which
frees you from suffering
so yes you can be in tiravada and not be
on the path you can be non-terrorvada
and not be on the path
either way the only way you'll be on the
path is if you actually
are understanding the dhamma if you have
that right criteria
whereby understanding of wrong is wrong
and right is right
frees you from suffering wrong view is
wrong with your right view of rivalry
that's the sort of party and to what
extent thought upon us free from
suffering well the buddha said himself
the mount in himalayas and seven grains
of sand are left
so that's how much suffering sothman has
abolished the mountains of himalayas suffering his
the mountains of himalayas suffering his
abandon all he has left is these seven
grains of sand that's how much he is
left so you see how profound bright view is
so you see how profound bright view is
now you can take that further and
abandon these seven grains of sand as
well become another hunt and you have to
become another hunt and you have to
eventually but yeah
right view is not a joke and it's not
certainly something you get on account
information but at the same time it's not this
but at the same time it's not this
impossibility either
do you have your senses intact yes are
you like intellectually sound
yes can you think for yourself yes can
you restrain yourself
yeah of course you're aware of your
choices no excuse then for not getting the right
no excuse then for not getting the right
view
suttas are there it
ponder upon it so then you realize the
thing that impedes you
is what you just read so it's not the
lack of instruction or this or
oh they're making me do these things and
no it's your lack of faith
looking for faults lack of respect lack
of respect
lack of application
if you carry on you realize us so is
this the and they're fully dependent
upon you
so you can then choose to abandon him
i'll just read it he says he pays
respects he gives ear he listens to what's being
he gives ear he listens to what's being
said
then he hears the dhamma having heard
the dhamma he memorizes it
he examines the meaning of the teachings
examines the meaning i mean how
often that gets overlooked today oh
knowing the knowing is now now i know
that i know
what do you know what have you
understood please explain to me well i
can't put it in the words there is no
understanding then
i mean the way the monks back in the day
would know whether they are kind of
on the right path or not is they get
other monks to question them
and then they explain and the ones who
understood would say
yeah yeah what you're saying is
basically right because they understood
it they know what this person is talking
about so examine the meaning there's nothing
so examine the meaning there's nothing
mystical about it
oh i have this experience and you know
just it's it's
it's out of this world what is that is
this world what do you mean
is the buddha teaching that liberation
comes out of the experience from out of
this world
or comes out of full understanding upon
examining the meaning
ah full understanding upon examining the
meaning so it doesn't matter what
experience you have what matters whether
you understood it or not
so examining the meaning are you
examining the meaning
after you you land your ear not looking
for faults out of faith
okay so now day in day now day out
my practice is examining the meaning to
the point of understanding these
universal truths
the dharma that frees me from liability
to suffer
let alone any suffering right here right
now because without that
examining me um
you cannot gain a reflective acceptance
of those teachings you can't gain an
understanding no
if you do not examine the meaning
exactly just
magically somehow it cannot occur
so after gaining an understanding
you know what needs to be done zeal
effort springs up
when efforts brings up he applies his
will exactly
he understands what needs to be and you
can think about like oh you need to do
you need to fix something so you have
this idea they need to fix but you have
no clue how to go about it
how would you feel towards that prospect
because you don't know what you need to
do you don't know how to fix it
you don't even know exactly what needs
fixing but then imagine ah
this is what needs fixing and this is
how you do it
i do it right now you immediately
get inspiration to do it because now you
know what needs to be done and you know what
what needs to be done and you know what
needs to be done because you have
reflexively understood what needs to be
done and you're reflexible understood what
and you're reflexible understood what
needs to be done because you made the
effort to understand
the meaning of what needs to be done
it's not like i need to find the zeal
now it will be the result
of your understanding
the path is clear so so if
if you have no zeal means you like
understanding
right right so if you do not have energy
for practice
means you haven't understood it enough
so oh but i can't practice because i
don't have the energy no
you don't have the energy because you're
not practicing
because you will get the energy if you
start making the effort
to understand which will then start
increasing the clarity of what needs to
be done
energy will be the result of it
a lot of people actually say that i
don't have the
energy for practice anymore
well you're you've never had it yeah
exactly because energy video properly is
because energy video properly is
effortless
based upon mindfulness it's the result
of your correct seeing and understanding
the meaning that you pondered upon
the result of that the tireless energy
arose in me
yeah or even when they like just talk on
dharma the result of just that talk would be
the result of just that talk would be
tireless energy yeah that's what it says
he applies his world having applied his
will he scrutinizes
he resolutely strives that whole
tirelessly striving tireless yeah
so if you don't you don't have a clear
sight of what needs to be done
you have to that extent you don't have
energy
because if you see the path it needs to
be walked
and that's why the same for the same
reason i mean a slight kind of
detail but for the same reason he said
that a noble disciple
does not free himself from sensuality so
like sotapana sakagami doesn't quite
become monogamy yet
because he lacks faith to that extent
so in terms of so he has understood that
he got the right view
understood the way out of suffering but
there's still these residues of
sensuality ill will that now he needs to clarify
ill will that now he needs to clarify
the meaning of those even more
and if he does so the energy
resoluteness towards overcoming
sensuality will be the result of it
but he doesn't do that because he
doesn't really develop faith
in those directions so to speak as in
you found a doctor he cured you you see
for yourself now what health is but
there's still some
lingering symptoms that pop up both of
you disappear now from your overall view
disappear now from your overall view
of general health you're not terminal
anymore this is nothing but
this is nothing but
from the point of view of itself it's
still something it's still these
ailments that come up so now you just
need to develop faith a bit further
and start treating those ailments as
well so that the energy
then once you get to know how to deal
with the ailments on account of
reflecting upon it thinking upon it
the energy will be effortless it isn't
isn't it with all life's
goals as soon as you see it this is ah
that's how you do it
you see that in those like you know
genetic sort of motivational quotes it's
always that
it's just people don't even think about
it i know if you think about it
then wait a minute well i could actually
do this clarity of your
the more you think the more you ponder
the clearly becomes what needs to be
done so yeah it starts with that attitude
but that's why it's also important to
come across the right instruction that
tells you this
if i just tell you oh no practice of
dhamma it's about non-understanding
the more you practice the less you know
[Music] which you know i heard people say
which you know i heard people say
as a teaching like that's completely the
opposite
so now okay so it's about not knowing
so i must start forgetting even things i
know and if you think that's what the
and if you think that's what the
practice is well you found a really bad
doctor who's not a doctor yeah because if
who's not a doctor yeah because if
you're who's not just not curing you
he's basically making even more sick
because now you think that's what dhamma
is and you spend the rest of your life
applying the non-knowing of whatever
else contradictions you picked up
thinking you're practicing
oh you haven't if you reflect it
properly enough if you reflect properly
enough yeah
you would see that if you just started
reading the suit as you'd see wait this
doesn't make sense
yeah but some people maybe meant this
maybe it doesn't matter i will not
listen to that doctor because he's not
careful with his instruction
because oh yes yes i meant this but i
said the opposite
which self-respecting doctor would do
that well don't go out in the sun so the heat
well don't go out in the sun so the heat
can harm you
but no instead i tell you there is no
heat there is no cold there is nothing just
there is no cold there is nothing just
be here now
but there is heat and there is cold and
there are the effects of it that could
make your illness worse or better
oh well that's not a doctor you should
listen to
because he doesn't know what he's
talking about he himself obviously he's
not cured because if he were why would he
cured because if he were why would he
tell you the opposite
that's why it's impossible to do the
dumber rightly practice correctly
understood rightly and not get the results of it
rightly and not get the results of it
not be cured like the simile of the the
chick who's
the hand that sits on its eggs
if the hand sits on her eggs even if she
doesn't wish for her chicks to come up
and pierce out safely they will
because she's doing the work the other
hand doesn't sit on the eggs
even if she does wish me my chicks peers
out safely into this world they won't
because she's not sitting on the eggs
so if you're sitting on the eggs in
terms of if you're doing the practice
the results will have to come up
results of freedom from suffering that's
the freedom from liability to suffer
yeah yeah the results that are results
in the suit does not
oh i feel much better about myself thus
that's the result of the dhamma
nah that's just a result of you making
some sort of effort which is great
but not not the threshold not the bar
you need to be
you want to be striving for